Yanari
Shogun's
Homeland
Owari
Now then,
さて　前回土佐の鞘走山　清涼院護剣寺にて
last episode took place in the holy land for swordsmen —
Seiryouin Gokokuji temple in Mt. Sayabashiri, Tosa.
Shichika defeated the one who was Japan's strongest — his sister, Yasuri Nanami, whom many considered a monster.
実の姉にして　前日本最強
そして多くの者が異口同音に　化け物と呼んだ鑢七実を打倒し
In doing so, Shichika and Togame succeeded in obtaining their 7th sword, Akutou Bita, and are heading back to Owari.
７本目の刀「悪刀·鐚」の収集に成功した
鑢七花と奇策士とがめは　ここで一旦尾張へと向かったのであります
This place is huge...
でけえなあ
Can you really say that?
そなたが言うか
But it's different from the stunning and equally huge capital of Kyou...
でもさ　同じようなでけえ京の都のきらびやかさとは違って
This place feels kind of harsh to me.
何か厳しさっつうのがだんだん伝わってくるなぁ
家鳴将軍家のお膝元　武士の町だ
This is Yanari Shogun's homeland, a town of warriors.
Unlike Kyou, this place naturally has a far more strict, serious, and dignified atmosphere.
京とは違い　厳正厳粛にして威厳があるのは当たり前のことだ
When you cross this moat, it's all mansions.
堀を越えたら　屋敷町だ
Hey, Togame!
おい とがめ　見てみろよあそこの屋敷
Look at that mansion over there!
Look at how heavily decorated and colorful it is compared to all the others!
こんな雰囲気の中
一軒だけやたらに飾りたてて
派手な色を塗りたくってる空気読めないやつがいるぜ
The owner's sure got no sense of taste, and totally can't read the atmosphere!
What the heck is that??
何だあれあの屋敷　訳分からん金色のしゃちほこなんか載っけてるし
The roof has a ridiculous golden whale on top of it!
I'm not one to criticize, but there really are people like this wherever you go, aren't there?
俺もあんま人のことは言えないけど
ここでも空気読めないやつってのがいるんだな
That mansion is so gaudy!
悪趣味な屋敷だぜ
I wonder what kind of attention-seeker lives there?
どんな目立ちたがり屋の家なんだろうな
わたしの家だ
That's my house.
Bitou
Kanzashi
I'm going to the castle.
登城してくるでな　留守番をしておいてくれ
Watch the house while I'm out.
えっ　俺のことを城の連中に紹介するんじゃなかったのか
Weren't you going to introduce me to everyone at the castle?
There have been some changes to the rules lately, and now it's forbidden to take swords into the castle.
そのことだがな　少々事情が変わってな
刀を持っては行けなくなった
Well, it's a good opportunity for you.
まあ　いい機会だ　ここに慣れておけ
Get used to this place.
We'll be staying here while we gather information about the swords.
しばらくこの屋敷で暮らすことになるのだから
In this mansion?
この屋敷で
Yes, in this gaudy mansion.
うむ　この悪趣味な屋敷でだ
She's not going to let that go...
根に持ってる
See you later.
では行ってくる
There's nothing here...
何もねえのな
Togame...
とがめ　覚悟の旅だったんだな
You were prepared for this journey, weren't you...
I wonder if Togame's doing work there right now...
今ごろ　あそこで仕事してんのかな
I guess I'll train or something.
稽古でもすっか
久しからず
Short time no see.
久しぶり というほどではないな　虚刀流
It hasn't been long enough to say
"long time no see" has it, Kyotouryuu?
Emonzaemon...
右衛門左衛門　あんたいつの間にそこに
When did you get behind me?
I'm good at moving in the shadows.
得意なのだ　後ろを取るのが
あの鑢七実に勝利を収めたそうではないか
I heard you defeated Yasuri Nanami.
どうやってここに
How did you get here?
I just walked in.
普通に歩いてだ
Very witty.
頓知じゃなくて
I saw you as I was passing the gate.
門をくぐるときにお前の姿が見えたのでな
稽古の最中のようだったので声を掛けるのをためらった
You looked like you were busy training, so I didn't call out to you.
That's all.
それだけのことだ
If that's all it was, then don't sneak up behind me.
それだけのことで後ろを取るな
失礼したな
Pardon me.
とがめならいないぜ
If you're looking for Togame, she isn't here.
Yes, I'm aware.
ああ知っている
だからこそ　わたしはここに来たのだ
And that's why I've come here.
That's why?
だからこそ
Did Princess-whatever send you on some task?
えっと　何とか姫の使いってこと
Princess Hitei.
否定姫だ
Don't ever call her Princess-whatever again.
何とか姫などと二度と言うな
悪かった
Sorry.
で　城で何かあったのか
So did something happen at the castle?
Where's Togame?
とがめは
Don't worry, nothing has happened.
心配せずともそういうことではないよ
Princess Hitei just wanted to pass along some information about the Deviant Blades, so I've come here to get you.
姫さまが変体刀の情報を奇策士殿に与えようと言うので
だからお前を呼びに来たのだ　虚刀流
Is that right?
そういうことか
What do you mean "is that right"?
何がそういうことだ　まったく
Geez...
のこのこ連れられてきよって
You just had to go and follow him, didn't you?
そなたさえ来なければ
If you hadn't shown up, I would have been able to use you as an excuse to go home without meeting that unpleasant woman.
それを口実にあの不愉快なやつに会わずに帰ることもできたというのに
Sorry.
ごめん
尾張に帰り着くなりこれだ　一本取られたとしか言いようがない
So it's come down to this right after we get back Owari...
All I can say is she got one up on us.
That woman...
あの女　目の上のたんこぶどころか
She's beyond a thorn in my side.
岩石　小惑星　いやなんだ
She's a... rock?
An asteroid?
No, beyond that...
似合い過ぎる　そのおかっぱ
That suits you too well!
That bobbed hair?
Short cut?
ざんぎり
お菊人形
Like a Kiku doll!
Hey, why not say "dot dot dot"?
ねえてんてんてんってやってみてよ
You look ten, no twenty years younger!
１０歳いや ２０歳は若く見える
Fraud?
詐欺　詐欺よね
This is fraud, right?
Are you done?
気が済んだか
I guess.
まあね
戻ったらいの一番に貴様に聞きたいことがあった
There was something I wanted to ask you once I'd returned.
何かしら
What might that be?
Were you aware that "cheerio" and "chesto" are different?
貴様「ちぇりお」と「ちぇすと」は違うと知っておったのではないか
What?
えっ　それ
That?
Oh, so you noticed?
なーんだ　気付いちゃったの
I thought I'd gained the upper hand on you this time too.
今度こそは蹴落としてやったつもりだったのにな
You have some amazing tenacity.
まったく貴様のしぶとさにはあきれ返るわ
Do you really have so many attachments left in this world?
そんなにもこの世に未練があるのか
I'm not so weak as to be defeated by those Maniwa Corps you released.
あんたが放った真庭忍軍ごときにつぶされるほどわたしは柔じゃないの
I'll come back from the dead as many times as it takes to expose your evil heart.
あんたの真っ黒な腹の中を全部暴くまでは
わたし何度でも蘇ってあげるから
No way, not a chance.
無駄だ無駄だ
貴様ごときに暴かれるほどわたしの腹の黒さは淡くはない
My evilness isn't so weak as to be exposed by the likes of you.
No matter how many times you come back, I will defeat you.
何度蘇ったところであっという間に蹴落としてやる
No, I'll trample you.
いや 踏みつぶしてやる
I deny it.
否定する　わたしはあんたのその言葉を否定する
I deny what you say.
You can't trample me any more.
あんたにはもう無理
In fact, I predict that I'll be the one to trample you.
それどころか逆にわたしがあんたを踏みつぶすと予言するわ
Go ahead and try.
やってみろ　黒さにおいて格の違いを思い知らせてやる
You will realize that the evil in my heart is on a totally different level from yours.
You're the one who needs to open your eyes.
思い知るのはあんたの方よ
Go make schemes or udon or whatever in the pits of hell.
地獄の底で奇策でもうどん粉でも練ってなさい
You're annoying.
やかましい　何だ貴様こそ その髪形 人のこと言えた義理か
Do you even have the right to say anything with that hair of yours?
Don't you know this is quite popular?
あらー　これなかなか評判いいのよ
Why don't you give it a try?
あんたもやってみれば
あっ　無理かあ
Ah, I guess you can't.
ごめんごめん
My bad.
まだ言うか　しつこい女だ
You're still on about that?
What an obstinate woman.
Thank you for the compliment.
褒めてくれてありがと
あいさつはこれくらいにして　本題に入るとするか
Enough with the greetings, let's get down to business.
Ah, yes.
ええ　そうね
あいさつ　今のが
Those were greetings?
あいさつといえば　七花君
Speaking of greetings, Shichika-kun...
Yeah?
はい
This is our first time meeting, right?
初めまして よねよろしく
Pleased to meet you.
Once again, I am Princess Hitei.
あらためまして　わたしが否定姫よ
どうも
Hi there.
Shichika! Don't bow your head to this woman!
七花　こんなやつに頭を下げるな
ごめん
Sorry.
Oh yeah...
そういえば あいつはどこに行ったんだ
Where did that guy go?
That guy?
あいつ　あー 右衛門左衛門のことね
Oh, Emonzaemon?
He's in the attic.
天井裏にいるわよ
あいつはとにかく不景気な面していて
That guy has such a depressing face, just looking at him makes me feel down.
見ているとこっちの気分まで沈んでくるからね
Depressing face? He's wearing a mask isn't he?
不景気な面って 仮面着けてるからだろ
I gave him that mask, actually.
あの仮面もわたしが与えた物なんだけどね
But even a mask can't hide his level of gloominess.
あいつの根暗さは仮面程度じゃ隠せるものじゃなかったのよ
I've never made Shichika do anything that dumb.
わたしは七花にそんな無茶を強要したことは一度もない
Shichika-kun's face doesn't seem to agree with you.
七花君の顔にはそう書いてないけどね
そんなことより刀の情報とは
Nevermind that, what's this information about the swords?
わたしを陥れるための策略ならやめておけ
And if you're trying to lure me into a trap, don't bother.
You don't have to be so wary.
心配しなくとも大丈夫よ
And in any case, why are you helping me out in the first place?
というよりなぜわたしに協力する
手柄を横取りするつもりか
Do you intend to take the credit?
Well, I've definitely thought of that.
まあー　そういうこともたくらんでいるわね
Collecting swords would be impossible for Emonzaemon, after all.
うちの右衛門左衛門じゃ　刀集めは無理だろうし
So?
で　所在不明所有者不明の残り５本の刀の情報を教えてくれようというのか
Are you saying you'll tell me something about the remaining five swords that we have absolutely no intel on?
I can't do that.
それは無理だけど　四季崎記紀に関する情報をね
This is information about Shikizaki Kiki.
Do you know Lake Fuyou in Edo?
江戸の不要湖知ってるわよね
Yeah, it's a designated first class disaster area, just like Mt. Shirei in Mutsu and Mt. Odori in Ezo.
蝦夷の踊山　陸奥の死霊山と並ぶ
一級災害指定地城の一つであろう
Right.
そう　その不要湖　四季崎記紀の工房があったらしいの
Apparently Shikizaki Kiki had a workshop at Lake Fuyou.
あそこに工房だと
A workshop? There?
Right.
そう　あのどうしたって人の住みようもない不要湖を
That uninhabitable region supposedly housed the headquarters of the legendary swordsmith.
あの伝説の刀かじは根城にしていたらしいの
But isn't Biyorigou there?
だがあそこには日和号があるであろう
「日和号」
Biyorigou?
Haven't you heard of it?
あなたも聞いたことがあるんじゃないかしら
They say Biyorigou roams Lake Fuyou, protecting something.
あの日和号は何かを守るために　あの不要湖にいるんじゃないかって
And suppose that what it's actually protecting is Shikizaki Kiki's workshop?
そう　その守るべき物が四季崎記紀の工房だったとしたら
われわれ真庭忍軍が得ている刀の所在は３カ所
We've obtained the locations of three swords.
Shireizan in Mutsu, Tendou in Dewa, and Lake Fuyou in Edo.
陸奥の死霊山　出羽の天童　そして江戸の不要湖だ
そうだな　出掛けてみるか
I suppose.
We'll head there.
Oh?
そうだったら　案内を付けるわ
In that case, he'll guide you.
勝手にしろ
Whatever.
By the way...
ところで
そこの床の間の物
That alcove there...
その変な鉄の塊みたいなものは何だ
What is that weirdly-shaped iron thing there?
Nothing really, just a decoration.
別に　ただの飾りよ
貴様の趣味らしくもないようだが　誰かに押し付けられたか
It doesn't suit your tastes.
Was it a present from someone?
I can throw it into Lake Fuyou for you if you want.
何なら不要湖に捨ててきてやってもよいぞ
ありがと　でもそれにはまったく及ばないわ
Thanks, but that's really not necessary.
七花
Shichika!
ごめん
Sorry!
And so we'll have Umigame go collect the sword in Shinano.
では　信濃にある刀の収集は海亀に行ってもらうとする
I think that's a good idea.
はい　それがいいかと思います
All right.
Leave it to me.
任せておけ
Though,
にしても　まだその刀の名も形も所有者も分からぬままだ
we haven't any information on which sword it is, nor the owner.
S-S-Sorry...
すすすみません　信濃のどこかの禅寺の塔頭に　あるってことしか
We only know it's in a temple somewhere in Shinano...
その　寺の特定が　あのできなくって
but not which one...
Well for now, I'll head there.
まあ取りあえず 出向いてみる
There should be no one to stand in my way.
今のところわしらを邪魔する者はおらんだろう
If we find out anything more, w-we'll get in touch with you.
詳しい情報が入りしだい　ごっ　ご連絡します
Thanks.
頼む
では早速
I'll be off then.
We're counting on you.
頼んだぞ
とがめ　疲れたのか
Are you tired, Togame?
Is it that obvious?
そう見えるか
Let me carry you.
おぶってやる
じゃあ こう
Like this then?
じゃあ どう
How then?
That guy's ahead of us, so he won't see.
でもあいつ前にいるから見えないよ　こっち
It should be fine.
だから大丈夫だって
No, no...
You can walk then?
じゃあ歩けるのか
確かにもう足が棒だ
My legs are totally numb...
Come on then.
だったら
駄目　やっぱり駄目
No! Never mind!
いいって　大丈夫だって
It's fine I said!
But...
でも
Come on.
来いよ　ほら
You think so?
そうか
Don't be so stubborn.
意地張るなって
それにしても　右衛門左衛門殿
I must say though, Emonzaemon-dono...
I can see the Princess is overworking you, as always.
そなたのところのお姫さまは相変わらず人使いが荒いな
Needless concern.
及ばず　大したことではない
It's nothing much for me.
Oh yeah, you used to be a ninja, right?
ああ　そういえば元忍者だったか
それ故
I guess that's how you were able to follow us around on our journey.
そなたはわたしたちの旅路もこっそり付け回しておったのだったな
Also because it was my duty.
それも任故
ならば お姫さまの護衛の任は気にならぬか
Don't you also have to protect the Princess too?
That is also a needless concern.
それも及ばずだ
Unlike you, the Princess has few enemies.
奇策士殿と違い姫さまには表立った敵は少ない
Actually, her sole enemy is right here, so I need not worry.
いや唯一の敵が今わたしといるのだからそれも心配ない
着いたぞ この先が不要湖だ
We're here.
Lake Fuyou lies ahead.
わたしは別の任があるので これで
I have other duties, so I'll take my leave.
Oh, okay.
I guess he knew he'd be in the way.
邪魔と分かったんだろう まあよいではないか
Well, that's fine.
It's finally just the two of us together...
やっと２人きりになれたのだから
何
What?
ノリ悪っ
What a followup...
Wait, I don't understand...
いやっ 意味分からなくて とがめさん
Togame-san?
Watch where you're stepping.
足元に気を付けるのだぞ
All right.
Though is there really a lake under this?
それにしても 本当にこの下に湖なんてあったのかな
誰かいるのか
Is someone there?
何だがらくたか
What is that? Some kind of junk?
日和号だ
That's Biyorigou.
Hey, it's got a sword.
おい刀持ってんぞ
Yeah, but we should be fine at this distance.
ああだがこの距離なら大丈夫だ
So what do we do?
でどうする
Let's observe for now.
まずは様子見だ
いいか七花
Listen Shichika, we're not looking to settle this right now.
今日今ここで決着をつけることが目的ではないからな
Got it.
分かってるよ
Though having said that, I know fighters get riled up.
とか言っているが 剣士はすぐに熱くなるからな
I said I get it!
だから分かってるって
If we can find Shikizaki's workshop, it'll help us a lot for the remaining swords.
四季崎の工房を探り当てれば今後の刀集めにとって有益になる
ならば その番人の日和号を打破する必要がある
Which means we'll need to defeat that guard.
その奇策を練るには こいつのことをもっと知らねばならん
To come up with a plan for that, I need to know more about that thing.
I see.
So, go.
ならば行け
Human recognized.
人間認識人間認識
Togame!
とがめ 刀だ
It's a sword!
やはりな
I thought as much.
No, I don't mean what it's holding.
違う その刀じゃない
This thing is—
こいつが
Yeah, I know.
ああ 分かっておる
この日和号そのものが「微刀·釵」だ
Biyorigou itself is Bitou Kanzashi.
One of the 12 leaders of the Maniwa Corps and the head of the fish squad, Maniwa Umigame.
真庭忍軍十二頭領が一人 真庭魚組指揮官 真庭海亀と見受ける
何だお主は
Who are you?
How do you know of the supreme awesomeness, power, and wealth of Maniwa Umigame?
どうしてわしが最高カッコ良くて最高いかした最高強い
最高モテモテ最高金持ちの真庭海亀だと知っておる
I don't recall introducing myself.
名乗った覚えもないのだがな
My name is Souda Emonzaemon.
わたしは左右田右衛門左衛門という
「長寿の海亀」などというから
When I heard the name "Sea turtle the long-lived" I thought you'd be an older person, but you seem quite young.
てっきりご老人だと思っていたのに ずいぶんとお若い
わしが最高カッコ良くて最高いかした最高強い
You may have realized my supreme awesomeness, ridiculous power,
awesome strength, wealth, and popularity just by looking at me,
最高モテモテ最高金持ちなのは見たら分かるとしても
but I'm surprised you know my other title...
二つ名まで知っておるとは
まあいい
Well that aside, what business do you have with me?
それで何だ わしは火急の用で先を急ぐ
I have pressing business to attend to.
Don't get in my way.
邪魔をするな
Unfortunately, it is my task to get in your way.
残念だが邪魔をするのがわたしの仕事だ
誰の差し金か
On whose orders?
Unanswerable.
答えず
もしやお前否定姫
Might you possibly be Princess Hitei's...
I see.
そうか　俺たちが奇策士の姉ちゃんに頼まれて姫をたばかったので
The strategian hired us, and then we betrayed the Princess, so she's out for revenge now?
その意趣返しというわけか
No.
いいや
違うとなると
If that's not it then...
逆に問うがお前がこの信濃の地まで来たのは
Let me ask in turn.
You came to Shinano to find one of Shikizaki Kiki's Deviant Blades, correct?
四季崎記紀の変体刀の１本を収集するためだろう
Who knows.
さあ どうかな
Well it's certainly true that Entou Jyuu was located here.
確かに「炎刀·銃」がここにあったのは間違いではない
刀の種類を知っているのか
You know which sword it is?
しかも「あった」とはどういうことだ
And what do you mean by "was"?
Unanswerable.
答えず
お前たち忍者は歴史の黒子にすぎない
Ninjas have historically acted only in the shadows.
これ以上炎刀に近づけば歴史的真実にたどりつくことになってしまう
If you get any closer to Entou, you will learn historical truth.
かませ犬には役者不足だ
That's too big a burden for an underdog such as yourself.
What do you mean? I don't get what you're saying.
何を言っておるのだまるで分からぬ
You don't need to, because you are going to die here.
分かる必要はない
お前はどうせここで死ぬ
えええっちょっと待て
W-Wait a second!
Quite frankly, while the others are all gung-ho for this sword hunt, I'm not really the same!
ぶっちゃけ　ほかのやつらはみんな刀集めに必死だけどな
わしはちょっと違う
Shinano is a nice place, and I heard the soba is good,
ここだって信濃はいい所でそばもおいしいって聞いたし
so I'm only 30% here for the sword, and 70% for my own enjoyment!
刀集め３物見遊山７ぐらいの割合でだから
So come on...
Let me introduce myself again.
あらためまして 名乗りをば
I am one of the 12 Maniwa Corps heads, Maniwa Umigame,
真庭忍軍十二頭領が一人 真庭海亀
also known as Sea turtle the long-lived.
通称「長寿の海亀」 推して参る
剣術使いか
So you know how to wield a sword..
それも洋刀
And a western sword, at that.
Ironic, isn't it?
皮肉なもんだな
You wield a Japanese sword.
そのなりのお主が日本刀を使うとは
長寿　すなわち不死身
"Long-lived", in other words, invulnerable.
巨大組織の中でのうのうと暮らしているお主とは
For one such as you, living comfortably in your big city, the number of battles we've fought cannot be compared!
くぐってきた修羅場の数が違うわ
I will teach you why the sea turtle is the strongest creature in the sea!
海亀こそが母なる海で最強の生き物だということを教えてやろう
I've advertised this inn,
いや　はたごの看板を掲げてはおりますが
but we still rarely get customers these days, so we don't have much in the way of entertainment here.
今ではお客人などめったにいなく　大したおもてなしもできず
いやいや　構わない
It's fine, don't worry about it.
They say that long ago there was a beautiful lake here,
昔は美しい湖であったようですが　今はもう
but now...
それにしても　あのようながらくた
Though, what business might you have in that junk pile?
It might look like a junk pile to you, but not to us.
皆にとってはがらくたかもしれぬが
わたしらにとってはそうでもないのだ
Really?
道具屋さんっていうのは大変なんですね
I guess it's hard work running a tool shop.
Ah, that's right!
ああそうだ　これなんですがね
This plate was passed down by my grandfather, who in turn got it from his grandfather.
死んだじいちゃんがひいじいちゃんから言い付かったのだが
He said it's very precious, so I should take care of it, but what do you think?
大層な物だから大事にしろって言うんですが
Yes, I'd say it's true.
うむ　その言葉に偽りはない
これは梅右衛門作に相違ない
There's no mistaking that this is of Ume'emon make.
Take good care of it.
大切にするのだな
Oh really?
ならば　盗っ人に狙われないようにしまっておくかな
I guess I should put this somewhere burglars won't find it then.
No, if you did that, it'd become more of a target.
いや そうすればかえって見つけやすくなるだろう
It'd be better to...
むしろ
If you were to use it as a milk saucer or something, it'd be safer.
あの猫の皿として日ごろ使っている方がかえって安心だ
No thief would think a milk saucer could be valuable treasure.
まさかお宝を猫の皿にしているとは盗っ人も気付くまい
Now that's a good idea!
そりゃ名案だ
It's a scheme.
奇策だろ
I don't know when sea turtles became the masters of the sea, but...
いつから海亀が海の生態の頂点になったかは知らんが
いや　なってはいない
No...
They never did.
You're a ninja.
お主　忍者であろう
Not anymore,
今は違う
but I was originally in the Aioi Corps.
だが元
相生忍軍
相生　聞いたことねえな
Aioi?
Can't say I've heard of it.
I see.
そうか
Then let me tell you.
ならば教えてやろう
相生忍軍とは今から１７０年前
The Aioi Corps were a ninja village that was destroyed 170 years ago by the Maniwa Corps.
お前たち真庭忍軍に滅ぼされた　忍びの里だ
Maniwa Kenpo!
「真庭剣法」
これぞ
This...
これぞ「相生拳法·背弄拳」だ
This is Aioi Kenpo,
Hairouken.
Why you...
てってめえ　ふざけやがって
Damn you!
It's hard to believe we lost to people of your level.
その程度の忍びに滅ぼされたとはな
You said earlier that the number of battles we've fought cannot be compared.
くぐってきた修羅場の数が違うか そのとおりだ
You are exactly right.
The nature of the battles we've fought are different.
お前とわたしとではくぐってきた修羅場の質が違う
戦国時代の技をたった一人残ったわたしが受け継いだ
I am the sole inheritor of the skills that were used in the Sengoku period.
今の真庭忍軍など相手にはならん
The Maniwa Corps of today are no match.
Well, besides Maniwa Houhou, that is.
もっとも　真庭鳳凰は別か
You know about Houhou?
お主　鳳凰のことを
You needn't know.
知るに及ばず
「不忍法·不生不殺」
No sneaking, no sparing, no killing
人鳥　鴛鴦　鳳凰
Pengin... Oshidori... Houhou...
The long-lived Umigame...
わしはもう
長寿の海亀　短命に
...has become...
死す
...short-lived...
無念なり
It's called "Kanzashi", so I thought...
「釵」なんて言うからてっきり
Like with Zokutou Yoroi, it'd be a sword in the shape of a hairpin.
「賊刀·鎧」のときみたく
そのままかんざしを模した刀なのかもしれないなって俺は思ってたけど
Well, one should avoid making things too similar.
まっ 同工異曲は避けんとな
それは四季崎記紀の話をしてるんだよな
You're talking about Shikizaki Kiki, right?
人形が刀だなんて
For a doll to be a sword...
Well, I guess it's sort of like Yoroi.
鎧が出てきたあたりでもう
But the Deviant Blades have too much design freedom...
四季崎の変体刀　自由過ぎだな
Well, it's like this.
こう考えてはどうだ　そなたは人間でありながら刀だろう
You're a human, yet also a sword.
Yeah.
So you can think of Biyorigou as being a sword and a doll.
であれば日和号は人形でありながら刀ということではないか
Which means Biyorigou is pretty typical of the Deviant Blades.
ならば日和号はかなり変体刀らしい変体刀であろう
I guess it's how you look at it.
物は言いようだな
あっ　そうだ
Oh, right...
聞こうと思ってて
I wanted to ask, but Emonzaemon was around so I couldn't before.
でもずっと右衛門左衛門がいてできなかったんだけど
Oh?
ほう　そなたも場の空気が読めるようになったのか
You're starting to learn what the appropriate time and place for things are.
I guess...
まあな
I wanted to ask, who is Princess Hitei?
あのさ　否定姫
あいつ何者なんだ
The color of her eyes and hair are...
ほら髪の色と目の色がさ
That woman is like me in that her origins are unknown.
あの女も私と同じで 出自は不明だ
ふん　なあ　それにしてもとがめ
Well that aside, why are you on such bad terms with her?
否定姫とはどうしてあんなに仲が悪いんだ
Why?
どうしてって
Well, we just don't get along.
まあ　馬が合わない
あいつは私が何度蹴落としてもはい上がってくる
No matter how many times I defeat her, she finds some way to crawl back.
She's so persistent.
しぶとい
You're the same way.
それはとがめもそうだろう
Don't lump us together!
一緒にするな
ていうか やけに気にしておるな あの女のことを
And wait, you seem quite interested in her...
いや そういうことじゃなくて
No, not really...
いつかまたぶつかることもあるんだろうなって
I was just thinking that we'll be running into her again.
When that happens, I'll be fighting Emonzaemon head on.
そのとき俺はあの右衛門左衛門と真っ向
そんなにあの女のことが気になるか
Are you that interested in that woman?
Don't tell me you've fallen for her?!
まさか 心変わりとかではあるまいな
She's your archenemy.
とがめの天敵だ　気になって当然だろ
It's natural for me to be interested in her.
W-Well...
それならよいのだ
It's fine if that's all it is.
Revenge!
仕返しだ
何をする
What are you doing?!
In the same way,
そういう意味じゃ　まにわにの動向も気になってんだよな
I'm interested in the Maniwani too.
Well, even though we have an alliance, we need to stay alert.
まあ 同盟を交わしたといっても気を抜くわけにはいかぬよ
I wonder what they're up to now?
今ごろあいつら どこでどうしてんのかな
Who knows.
さてな
I'm sure they're playing the underdog somewhere.
どうせどこかでかませ犬の役割でも演じておるのではないか
I have returned.
ただ今戻りました
As planned, I guided the strategian Togame and Kyotouryuu to the destination,
予定どおり　奇策士とがめと虚刀流を送り届けた後
真庭忍軍の十二頭領の一人 真庭魚組指揮官
then dealt with one of the 12 Maniwa Corps heads and the leader of the fish squad, Maniwa Umigame.
真庭海亀を始末してまいりました
You're late.
だから遅いって
Seems the Maniwa Corps couldn't be taken lightly, as you said.
あんたの言うとおり 真庭忍軍も侮れなかったわね
I deny what I said a month ago.
１カ月前の自分をわたしは否定するわ
それにしてもあんたもちょっとはすっきりしたんじゃない
Though I must say, you seem rather calm.
Weren't you able to avenge your ancestors?
ご先祖さまの恨みを晴らせたでしょ
１７０年も前の恨みを１７０年後の彼らで晴らす意味はないと考えます
I see no reason to avenge a 170 year old grudge.
そのような私情を持って
I don't intend to put my personal feelings before my duties to you.
姫さまから与えられた任務に臨むつもりは
あーあ いちいち堅っ苦しいのよあんたは そういうのうざいっての
It's annoying how you're always so boring like that.
So, how's that unpleasant woman doing?
で あの不愉快な女の方はどうなったわけ
She has most likely encountered Biyorigou already.
おそらくは日和号と接触は果たしているでしょう
I wonder if she's realized that Biyorigou is actually Bitou Kanzashi yet?
ちゃんと気付いているかしらね 日和号が微刀釵だって
As Kyotouryuu is able to sense the swords, they must have already.
虚刀流が持つという共感覚があれば たやすいことでしょう
I wonder.
どうかしら
Though, Shichika...
七花
それにしても そなたの共感覚は便利極まりないな
Your sixth sense isn't necessarily advantageous.
あんまり頼りにされても困るんだけどな
I guess we can't rely on it too much.
Princess Hitei probably doesn't know that Biyorigou itself is a Perfected Deviant Blade, right?
否定姫は日和号自体が完成形変体刀であると
見抜いていたわけじゃないんだよな
No, I'm sure she's aware.
いや 見抜いておったろうよ
Why didn't she just tell us from the start then?
じゃあ 最初からそう言えばいいじゃん
おおかた
Maybe she thought it'd be interesting if I didn't realize it and got torn apart, or something like that.
わたしがそれに気付かずに日和号を破壊してしまったら面白いとか
考えていたのであろうよ
でもさ そんないたずらめいたまねを仕掛けてはいるものの
But despite the tricks she plays on you, she's still helping you out on the sword hunt, right?
否定姫はとがめの刀集めに
取りあえずは協力してくれようってわけなんだよな
Or so it seems.
のようだな
手柄を横取りしようとたくらんでおるのか
She may be planning to steal all the credit from me at the end, or waiting for me to fail.
わたしがすきを見せるのを待っておるのか
まあ それはこちらにしても同じことだが
That said, the same goes for me.
怖っ
Scary!
It didn't seem like he noticed this one, after all.
だって そこのそれには気付かなかったみたいだし
It's not a very reliable sixth sense is it?
案外頼りない感覚なんじゃないの
Wouldn't it be fun if Shichika-kun didn't notice and got destroyed by Biyorigou?
まあ 七花君が気付かないまま 日和号を破壊しちゃってたら
それはそれで面白いわよね
刀集めなのに刀本体を壊しちゃったんなら台無しだもん
If he got killed by a sword while on a sword hunt, the whole venture would be ruined.
I wonder if that unpleasant woman would be executed or slice her own stomach?
あの不愉快な女 首が飛ぶか腹を切るか
どっちになるかしら
Your traps are certainly spiteful.
意地の悪い仕掛けを打ちますね
Whatever.
いいじゃない ちょっとは遊ばせてもらわなくっちゃ
I'm bored, so let me play around a bit.
とにかく まずは目の前のことだ
Well, let's focus on what's at hand first.
Biyorigou before anything else?
差し当たっては日和号のことだな
Hey, don't suddenly move like that.
あっおい急に動くな
Oh, okay.
Come on...
ほらほら どうだほら
How's that? What now?
Hey, stop! Come on!
こら よせ
よさぬか
I'm over here!
ほら ほら
What are you stupid?
バカか そなたは
Geez...
もう
Ah, it's coming.
来たぜ
Wait, Shichika.
待って　七花
Don't do anything yet.
まだ手を出すな
This is already the third day...
つったってもうこれで３日目だぜ
We have to finish this first.
まずはこれを完成させねば
We need to find Shikizaki's workshop before we defeat Biyorigou?
日和号を倒すより
四季崎の工房がどこにあるか先に探るって聞いたけどさ
You seem dissatisfied.
不服そうだな
やっぱり何か　順番が逆な気がするんだけどな
I guess I feel like it should be the other way around.
Don't you know the saying "measure twice, cut once"?
「せいては事を仕損じる」ということわざを
知らんだろうな
I guess you wouldn't...
We'll clear out that area today.
今日はあっちの方を完成させるぞ
Yeah, yeah.
Are you serious?
それは本当か
U-Um... Yes...
えっえっと あっ はい
Your information is always correct,
お主の情報はいつも正確だ
だが今日ほどその情報が間違いであってほしいと願ったことはないぞ
but I've never hoped more for your information to be wrong than today.
すっ すみません
I'm sorry...
Who on earth killed Umigame-san?
いったい誰が海亀さんを
そのようなことをする人物といえば
The only person I can think of with the motive and capability of doing that has to be Owari's Princess Hitei.
尾張の否定姫に違いあるまい
よし できたぞ
All right, done.
これが不要湖の地図だ
This is a map of Lake Fuyou.
上から見たらこんな感じなのか
So it looks like this from above?
Well, there are probably a few mistakes.
さすがに誤差はあるだろうがな
わたしはこの手のことに強いのだぞ
I'm pretty good at this though.
でなければ このような刀集めの旅などできるわけがあるまい
If I weren't, there's no way we could have come this far on our sword hunt.
そういえばとがめと旅して道に迷ったことないな
Come to think of it, I've never gotten lost traveling with you.
３次元の空間把握能力は高い方だと自負しておる
I'm confident in my three dimensional spacial recognition skills.
見事なもんだん
It's quite something.
湖の中をうねっているこの細い線は何だ
What's this curvy line going through the lake?
少しは自分で考えろ
Think about it yourself.
Stop teasing and tell me!
いじわる言わずに教えてくれよ
Fine, okay! All right!
参った参った 分かった
日和号の軌道に決まっておろうが
It's Biyorigou's path, of course!
てっきり道なりに動いてるもんだとばかり思ってた
I thought it walks on a totally random path.
あっ たまに止まって日なたぼっこもしてたっけな
Sometimes it just stops and sunbathes for a while too...
日和号の軌道から察するに
Judging from the path Biyorigou takes, Shikizaki's workshop is probably around here.
おそらくここに四季崎の工房があったのではないかと思う
それを掘り出すのはまた後の話として
Digging it out is a problem for later.
Dig? Who?
掘り出す 誰が
そなたに決まっている
You, who else?
何か不満があるか
Got a problem with that?
いえ ありません
No, none...
Now, it's finally time to defeat Biyorigou,
さて いよいよ日和号を倒す時が来た
それも傷つけずに倒さねばならない
and you need to do it without damaging it.
そこでわたしの奇策だ
For that, I have a scheme.
Oh, here comes Togame's scheme!
おお 出た とがめの奇策
あっ 俺に何か手伝えることはあるか
Do I have a part in it?
そうだな 取りあえずわたしのことを抱き締めているがよい
Yeah.
First, hug me.
落とし穴か
A trap, huh...
さすがとがめの奇策
That's just like you to think of!
そうか こんなの朝飯前だ
Really? This was easy to come up with.
よしこれで日和号もイチコロだな
All right!
Biyorigou should be easy to deal with now!
来た
Here it comes!
All right!
よし
まただ
Again?
Look, it's sunbathing again.
日和号のやつ また日なたぼっこしている
It's not even paying attention to us...
ったく こっちの気も知らないで
As far as I can tell, that thing has four arms and four legs.
とどまるところ あいつには腕が４本脚が４本あるってことだ
I'm not an idiot, but...
俺もさ バカじゃないから いや バカなんだけど
Well, I guess I am, but...
あのさ 虚刀流は人間相手の格闘技だぜ
Kyotouryuu is a school for fighting against people, you know.
人形を相手にするなんて発想はなかった
I'd never imagined using it against a doll.
そもそも格闘技ってのは読み合いだ
And in the first place, martial arts is about being able to read your opponent.
相手が下段攻撃してくるときは
When my opponent strikes low, I block, then attack his vulnerable high spot.
それを防御しつつ 相手のがら空きになった上段を突く
投げ技をかけそうだったら 投げ抜ける
If he looks like he'll throw something, I dodge.
まあ 言ってみりゃ
Well, I guess it's kind of the same as when I lost to Konayuki because she had absolutely no tactics.
まったく策のない粉雪に俺が負けたのも同じことだ
だからあいつには 意表を突くための牽制も通じないし
Surprise attacks won't work on that doll, and—
Yeah, Shichika.
そうか七花
I understand your worries.
そなたの不安は よく分かった
I'm not really worried, but...
不安ってわけでもないんだけどさ
ならば 例によってわたしの奇策が必要だということだな
Then basically you're saying we need one of my schemes?
って その奇策今日失敗したじゃん
That scheme totally failed today...
よいよい 愚昧なるそなたに このわたしが知恵を授けてやろう
It's fine.
Let me impart some wisdom on you, since you're so dumb.
だからとがめの奇策も無駄じゃないかって
Like I said, your scheme totally fail—
いや その ごめん
Um...
Sorry.
T-Togame-san?
とがめさん
お遊びはこれまでだ
That's enough playing.
お遊び
Playing?
わたしの奇策が通じない相手がいるなどと
It's sad that you've come to worry that my schemes might actually fail against someone.
事もあろうにそなたに心配されてしまうとはな
いや だから
Well, I mean...
Whether human or doll, no matter what the situation, I will defeat them with schemes alone.
人間であろうと人形であろうと
どういう状況でも わたしはあくまでも奇策のみで切り抜けてきた
逆境も苦境も
Through trouble or hardship, that's how my daily life passes.
わたしの前ではひとしく日常にすぎん
よかろう
Listen, don't worry about that kind of stuff again.
二度とそんな的外れな心配ができぬよう
これを機会にそなたを教育してやる
Since we have the time, I'll educate you.
I'm not letting you sleep tonight.
今夜は寝かさぬぞ
明日 決着をつけよう
The showdown will be tomorrow.
Kyotouryuu: Rose!
「虚刀流·薔薇」
で 「虚刀流·百合」
Kyotouryuu: Lily!
Human recognized.
人間認識 即刻惨殺
Immediate termination.
斬殺できるもんなら斬殺してみろ
If you think you can terminate me, then go ahead and try!
そのころにはあんたを まあ八つ裂きにはできないんだけどな
However, by that point...
Well, I guess I can't tear you into pieces, but...
バカ はまってない
Idiot. Don't get riled up.
Kyotouryuu: Orchid!
「虚刀流·鷺草」
「虚刀流·石榴」から「菖蒲」まで
Kyotouryuu: Pomegranate into Iris, Hybrid Combo!
混成接続
七花
Shichika!
危ない危ない
That was close!
Restrict your attacks to strikes, got it?
いいか攻撃は
打撃系のみに限る
分かった
Got it.
どうせ 日和号に投げ技は通じねえ
Throws won't work on Biyorigou anyway.
Also, don't hit its head or chest.
それも頭部と胴体には当てるな
Okay.
しかしとがめもすげえこと考えるよな
Though that's quite a plan you came up with.
傷つけちゃいけないって縛りがあるところに
Forcing Biyorigou to defend itself since we're constrained to keeping it unharmed...
相手に勝手に防御させるって考え
意思のない人形をそういうふうに利用するとは
Using a doll without any will of its own like that...
まったく
でもやっぱり けん制が効かないってのは厄介だ
It's pretty annoying that feints don't work on it though.
こっちは体が覚えちゃってるからな
My body sometimes moves on its own.
無駄だと思っても
Even though I'm thinking it's pointless, I'll still throw in feints every now and then.
ついつい要所要所でけん制を入れちゃうし
Counterattack commencement.
反撃開始
Doll fatality: Tornado
「人形殺法·竜巻」
「人形殺法·旋風」
Doll fatality: Whirlwind
「人形殺法·春一番」
Doll fatality: Spring storm
Doll fatality: Squall
「人形殺法·突風」
そのほかはだいたいとがめの予想したとおりのようだな
It's doing pretty much what you predicted.
当然だ
Of course.
そなたの姉ほどではなくともな
I'm not at the level of your sister, but even I can see that much.
わたしだって見る目はあるのだ
Just looking at the way it's designed from the outside, you can tell what kind of movements it should be capable of.
外側から見ればそれがどういう動きをするのか
どういう動きが可能なのかくらいは見切れるとも
これでだいたい 日和号の動きが分かるはずだ
I'm pretty sure I've figured out all of Biyorigou's movements now.
これを把握するまで今夜は寝かさぬぞ
You're not allowed to sleep until you've memorized this.
All right.
あえて言うならわたしは見切るのでも見抜くのでもない
I daresay that it has nothing to do with giving up or seeing it through.
そなたを信じ ただ見守るしかない
All I can do is believe in you and watch.
信じているぞ 七花
I believe in you, Shichika!
だったら 俺は
Then I will...
Listen, Shichika.
いいか七花
I am a sword.
俺は刀だ
そしてお前もまた刀だ
And you are also a sword.
刀は斬れなければ意味はない
There is no meaning to a sword that doesn't cut.
まずはそのことを第一に考え
That is the first thing you must keep in mind.
All you need to be is a sharp sword.
お前はただ鋭き刀であればいい
俺がそうであったように
Just like I was.
どういう意味
What do you mean?
You'll understand some day.
そのうち分かる
今なら親父の言葉の意味が分かる
I understand what my father was saying now.
刀になるとは 気持ちを持つな 考えるな
As a sword, I don't need to have emotion, or to think, or feel anything!
感じるな という意味だ
Doll fatality: Whirlwind scythe
「人形殺法·鎌鼬」
とがめ　日和号はちょっと前の俺だ
Togame, Biyorigou is like how I was not long ago.
No determination or will, nothing to lose, no sense of justice,
覚悟決意もなく
何も捨てないで正義の心もなく ただ
とがめに言われるまま 刀集めをしていた俺だ
just doing what you commanded — hunting swords.
七花
Shichika...
That's why for the sake of the hunt I slew Koumori, Meisai, and Sabi without a second thought.
だから真庭の蝙蝠も 迷彩も錆も
刀を集めるために何の迷いもなく 斬った
でも意思を持たない刀のままだったら
But as a sword with no will of my own, I wasn't able to defeat Nee-chan.
俺は姉ちゃんに勝つことができなかった
ただ四季崎に命じられるまま 何百年も命令どおりに攻撃するこいつは
This doll, following the commands of Shikizaki that he gave how many hundreds of years ago, is like how I was.
ちょっと前の俺と同じだ
俺こんなふうに こんな機械人形みたいに戦ってたんだ
I used to fight like that doll.
きっとみんな ちっとも楽しくなかったんだろうな
I guess it wasn't fun for anyone.
Human recognized.
人間認識
俺にはお前が刀にしか見えないけれど
I can't see you as anything but a sword,
日和号 お前は俺を人間と言ってくれるんだな
but Biyorigou, you see me as a human!
Kyotouryuu: Magnolia!
「虚刀流·木蓮」
Doll fatality: Tempest
「人形殺法·嵐」
Kyotouryuu: Cherry!
「虚刀流·桜桃」
「人形殺法·砂嵐」
Doll fatality: Sandstorm
Kyotouryuu: Wild Strawberry!
「虚刀流·野苺」
Doll fatality: Typhoon
「人形殺法·台風」
とがめ
Togame.
俺もとがめを信じてその命令に従う
I obey your orders because I believe in you.
Even if this body is broken,
この身が折れようとも 俺は
I...
何だ
What?
「人形殺法·微風刀風」
Doll fatality:
Zephyr Swordstorm
おいおいマジかよ
Are you serious?
I can't believe you were right on...
まさかここまでとがめの予想どおりだなんて
見れば分かる 人形は人間と違って素直だ
You can tell just by looking.
Unlike humans, dolls are predictable.
とがめ
Togame!!
とがめ 俺もとがめを信じてるぞ
Togame, I believe in you.
命令に従うのも俺の意思でだ
I also obey you out of my own free will.
たとえこの身が折れようとも 俺はとがめを守る
Even if this body is broken,
I will protect you.
心にそう決めたぜ
That's what I've decided!
What are you talking about, after all this?
何をいまさら言っておる
Not because you ordered me to,
とがめに命じられたからじゃない
俺が人として この心でそう決めたんだ
but because I decided from the bottom of my heart, as a human.
俺は刀だが
I may be a sword,
but at the same time, I have a human soul!
同時に魂を持つ人間なんだから
七花
Shichika...
そろそろだな
It's about time.
Honestly...
やれやれ ずいぶんとかかってしまったようだが
We had to keep it occupied for a while, but it looks like its fuel has finally run out.
ようやく燃料切れか
思ったより軽いな
It's lighter than I thought...
じゃあのたまに日なたぼっこするみたいに立ち止まってたのが
So when it stopped to sunbathe occasionally,
燃料補給だったのか
it was actually recharging itself?
That's right.
そういうことだ
とがめ最初からそれを
Did you know that from the start?
まあどうしてこれが動いているかという素朴な疑問を解消した所から
Well, after I figured out how it kept moving all this time,
I worked my plans around it.
策を練ったまでのこと
問題は
The question was...
Whether Biyorigou would run out of fuel,
日和号の燃料とそなたの体力とどっちが早く底を突くかだった
or whether you'd run out of energy first.
でも俺の体力が勝つって勝算はあったのか
But were you sure my body would win?
勝つと思えば運命はそうなるとか言うつもりだろ
Or are you saying it was fate that I would win?
That's not it.
違うな
Fate is something you decide yourself.
運命は自分で言い張るものだ
「わたしはそなたを信じているからな」と言ったであろう
I told you I believe in you, right?
物は言いようだ
I guess it's how you see it.
さて 今のうちに手足を取り外しておかないとな
Now then, we should remove its limbs while we have the chance.
いつ何時
At any point it might—
I feel kind of sorry for it.
何かかわいそうだな
バカかそなたは 人形に感情移入してどうする
What are you stupid?
You don't need to empathize with a doll.
人の顔はしていても これはあくまでも完成形変体刀の１本
Even though it has a face, this is still one of the Perfected Deviant Blades, Bitou Kanzashi.
「微刀·釵」なのだぞ
Well...
刀に対する感情移入なら わたしが言っていいことではないか
I guess I don't have the right to say you shouldn't hold feelings for a sword.
結構かわいらしい顔してんだな
It's quite a pretty face.
四季崎記紀の趣味なのかな
I wonder if that was one of Shikizaki Kiki's hobbies.
東風吹かば 匂いおこせよ梅の花 主なしとて春を忘るな
"When the eastern wind blows, let out your scent.
Plum flower without a master, don't forget Spring."
After protecting that lake for how many hundreds of years after its creator died,
作り手も死に
主もないまま 数百年もの間あの不要湖を守り続けたこの人形には
確かにねぎらいの言葉の一つくらいは掛けてやってもよいのかもしれぬな
I suppose this doll deserves at least a word of thanks.
敵ながらあっぱれだ
It put up a good fight.
そうだ さっきのもう一回言ってみろ
Ah, right!
Say that line again!
"I believe in you!"
「俺はとがめを信じて」ってやつ
いいよもう
I can't say it again...
Come on, say it!
言ってみろって
いいって
No!
Just say it!
言えばいいじゃん
I said no!
だからいいって
釵ってのはさ
They say that Shikizaki Kiki modeled Kanzashi after the woman he loved when he was young.
四季崎記紀が生前に最も愛した女性を模して作ってあるんだってさ
笑っちゃうことにさ
That's pretty funny.
別に 笑うようなことではないと思いますが
I don't believe it's anything to laugh at.
わたしの言うことを否定するの
Are you denying what I say?
That's good; so you've finally figured out how to humor me?
いいじゃん
あんたもだいぶわたしの機嫌の取り方が分かってきたって感じ
あの不愉快な女はその後どうしたのかしら
I wonder what that unpleasant woman's going to do now...
日和号と報告書をこっちに送りつけて 帰ってこないつもりなの
Does she not plan on returning after sending Biyorigou and her report here?
It appears she is staying back at Lake Fuyou in order to find Shikizaki Kiki's workshop.
いえ 不要湖で四季崎記紀の工房の発掘作業をしているようです
Ah, she's making Shichika-kun work?
あら 七花君にやらせているのね
She pushes people too hard.
まったく人使いが荒いわね
それにしても 工房に何か情報があると思っているのかしら
Though do you think that workshop might have any information in it?
真庭鳳凰より得ている刀の在りかは天童
The location of the sword that Maniwa Houhou told her of was Tendou.
その情報の真偽を確かめるつもりかと
She will likely go to ascertain the validity of that information.
あ 本当に天童にあるんだったわね
Ah, there really is one in Tendou isn't there?
Which one was it again?
あそこのは何だっけ
Outou Nokogiri.
「王刀·鋸」です
それよりさ
Really, though...
姫さま
Princess?
What a hassle.
やっぱり邪魔よね
邪魔 私がですか
Hassle?
Are you referring to me?
You're always a hassle.
あんたが邪魔なのはいつものことでしょ
真庭忍軍のことよ
I'm talking about the Maniwa Corps.
真庭忍軍については 放っておけばいいと
I believe you said we can ignore them.
そんな過去の自分を否定するわ
I deny what I said in the past.
残りは確か３人よね
There are three left, right?
あんたさ
I want you to go find Maniwa Houhou...
ちょっと真庭鳳凰を
暗殺してきなさいよ
...and assassinate him.
What is it?
何だ 何かあったか
Did you find something?
I don't know what it is, but it's really heavy.
何か分かんないけど ずっしり重いし
開けてみるか
Should I open it?
We don't care about a box right now!
箱など今は関係ない
Find the workshop first!
工房を探るのが先だ
Just throw that away!
そんなものは捨てておけう
After fighting the soulless, masterless doll, the human sword Yasuri Shichika has learned what it means to have a human soul.
魂もなくた だあるじの命に忠実であった人形との戦いで
人の心の意味を知った人間刀鑢七花
奇策士とがめとの刀集めの旅もいよいよ佳境に入ったところで
He is finally entering the climax of the sword hunt with the Strategian Togame.
今月こよいの『刀語』 お楽しみはここまでにございます
The story of Katanagatari on this month and this evening...
ends here.
kataranaide karatanai sugata
Speak not, unspeaking shadow
tamatebako ni tsumetara nemuremasuka
Dare you sleep with such treasures in your chest?
ugokidasu kezurareru mama no karada
The body riven comes alive
koubuku no ibuki sosogu
Perfume of the juniper, a mist upon it
omoidase katachi wa hito wo mu ni shite
Remember! Form leads man to ruin
yasuragi ni kaeru no
Leave the path and find peace
aa karakuri no ito wa toumei dakara kirai
Ah, how I loathe puppet strings as they are unseen
語らないで　語れない姿
hikichigiru hitori de toberu
Tear them from their post and fly alone!
玉手箱に詰めたら眠れますか
odoranai no odoranai sugata
Dance not, undancing shadow
arimukashi wo e ni shita otogibanashi
A fairy tale of what has long past
kataranaide kataranai sugata
Speak not, unspeaking shadow
動き出す　切られるままの体
tamatebako ni tsumetara nemurarete ne
Dare you sleep with such treasures in your chest.
孤独の息吹注ぐ
思い出せ　形は人を無にして
安らぎに帰るの
からくりの糸は　透明だから嫌い
Biyorigou was quite the tough opponent
but it's all going according to my clever plan!
I can't believe Shichika said something embarrassing like "Togame, I believe in you!"
引き千切る　一人で飛べる
Now then, the next sword wielder is Dewa's writing woman warrior.
踊らないの　踊れない姿
Shichika doesn't have to get along that well with her!
在る昔を絵にした踊りわたし
I won't lose to these feelings of jealousy!
語らないで　語れない姿
Anyway, next time on Katanagatari: Otou Nokogiri
Otou
Nokogiri
Cheerio!
玉手箱に詰めたら眠られたね